<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Tag: Type Providers | Functional Flow]]></title>
  <link href="http://functionalflow.co.uk/blog/tags/type-providers/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://functionalflow.co.uk/"/>
  <updated>2015-12-20T01:09:03+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://functionalflow.co.uk/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Gustavo Guerra]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Importing Messages from Windows Phone to Android]]></title>
    <link href="http://functionalflow.co.uk/blog/2015/12/20/importing-messages-from-windows-phone-to-android"/>
    <updated>2015-12-20T01:05:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://functionalflow.co.uk/blog/2015/12/20/importing-messages-from-windows-phone-to-android</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Searching around the web I couldn't find any way to to transfer messages from Windows Phone to Android that actually worked.</p>

<p>I could export all the data from Windows Phone using the <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-gb/store/apps/contacts-message-backup/9nblgggz57gm">contacts+message backup app</a>, but there was no Android app that understood that .msg format.</p>

<p>However, I found the <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.riteshsahu.SMSBackupRestore&amp;hl=en">SMS Backup &amp; Restore app</a> that seemed to work well for exporting/importing messages between Android devices.</p>

<p>So with a bit of trial and error and the help of the <a href="http://fsharp.github.io/FSharp.Data/library/XmlProvider.html">XML Type Provider</a> I managed to create an F# script to convert from one format to another.</p>

<p>The trickier part was trying to figure out what DateTime format was being used in both cases (thanks <a href="https://twitter.com/LincolnAtkinson/status/678314345508433921">Lincoln</a>), all the rest was pretty straightforward. The .msg format has a lot less fields than the .xml format used by the Android app, but it ended up still working ok with those missing fields.</p>

<p>It converts both SMS and MMS, though it only retains the text and photos from the MMS's, vCards, embedded location maps and other items are skipped. but it should be fairly easy to add that support if needed.</p>

<p>Here is the code:</p>

<script src="https://gist.github.com/ovatsus/2dd82172dcd8308d559c.js"></script>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[FSharp.Data 2.0.0 released]]></title>
    <link href="http://functionalflow.co.uk/blog/2014/03/10/fsharp-data-2-0-0-released"/>
    <updated>2014-03-10T02:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://functionalflow.co.uk/blog/2014/03/10/fsharp-data-2-0-0-released</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Version <a href="http://www.nuget.org/packages/FSharp.Data/2.0.0">2.0.0</a> of <a href="http://fsharp.github.io/FSharp.Data/">FSharp.Data</a> was just released. You can get the full version history on the <a href="https://github.com/fsharp/FSharp.Data/blob/master/RELEASE_NOTES.md">release notes</a>, but here are the highlights:</p>

<ul>
<li>A new type inference algorithm that will generate better and more robust API's in the presence of missing and heterogeneous types. This means that you'll get much less errors when using JsonProvider and XmlProvider on real world messy files. The error messages are now also more descriptive when things go wrong.</li>
<li>Much improved Freebase support for individuals.</li>
<li>The functionality of the Http class was greatly extended. It now supports uploading and downloading binary files, and compression across all supported platforms, among many other tweaks.</li>
<li>Improved the overall performance of the type provider itself when running inside the editor, and also of the generated code.</li>
<li>The documentation was much improved, there's now a Japanese translation of it, and comprehensive reference documentation.</li>
<li>Mono is now fully supported, as well as F# 3.1, and the new Portable Class Library profile 7.</li>
<li>Source link support. This means that you can step trough the source code while debugging if you enable that feature in Visual Studio.</li>
</ul>


<p>We also took the opportunity of major version bump to do some house cleaning, so things that we weren't previously very happy with were renamed, dropped or, shuffled around. Unfortunately this means breaking changes, but we think the overall outcome is positive. In this process we dropped support for:</p>

<ul>
<li>Silverlight and Windows Phone separate packages.</li>
<li>Apiary provider (which has now moved to a <a href="https://github.com/fsprojects/ApiaryProvider">separate project</a>).</li>
</ul>


<p>Thanks to everyone which contributed directly to this release, <a href="http://github.com/tpetricek">Tomas Petricek</a>, <a href="http://github.com/dsyme">Don Syme</a>, <a href="http://github.com/forki">Steffen Forkmann</a>, <a href="http://github.com/enricosada">Enrico Sada</a>, <a href="http://github.com/ctaggart">Cameron Taggart</a>, <a href="http://github.com/remkoboschker">Remko Boschker</a>, <a href="http://github.com/vasily-kirichenko">Vasily Kirichenko</a>, <a href="http://github.com/diegofrata">Diego Frata</a>, <a href="http://github.com/yukitos">yukitos</a>, <a href="http://github.com/OkayX6">Denis Ok</a>, and <a href="http://github.com/jamesholwell">James Holwell</a>, and also to everyone who also contributed indirectly through yak-shaving needed in <a href="http://tpetricek.github.io/FSharp.Formatting">FSharp.Formatting</a>, <a href="http://fsharp.github.io/FSharp.Compiler.Service">FSharp.Compiler.Services</a>, and <a href="http://fsharp.github.io/FAKE">FAKE</a>, including <a href="http://github.com/7sharp9">Dave Thomas</a>, <a href="http://github.com/soloman817">Xiang Zhang</a>, <a href="http://github.com/dungpa">Anh-Dung Phan</a>, <a href="http://github.com/fbmnds">fbmnds</a>, and <a href="http://github.com/mexx">Max Malook</a>. And also thanks to everyone who contributed by just placing issues on github, but I couldn't find a way to generate a list of all of you.</p>

<p>There's still a lot of room for improvement, and we love pull requests, so please contribute, even if it's only fixing a typo in the docs. A getting started guide is available <a href="http://fsharp.github.io/FSharp.Data/contributing.html">here</a>.</p>

<p>For the next versions, we want to add:</p>

<ul>
<li>Html type provider, currently being worked on by <a href="http://github.com/colinbull">Colin Bull</a>, <a href="http://github.com/mathias-brandewinder">Mathias Brandewinder</a> and me.</li>
<li>Write API for Json, currently being worked on by <a href="http://github.com/pezipink">Ross McKinlay</a>.</li>
<li>Authentication support, currently being worked on by <a href="http://github.com/veikkoeeva">Veikko Eeva</a>.</li>
<li>XSD support, which I hope one of you reading this will pick up :).</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[FSharp.Data 1.1.9 released]]></title>
    <link href="http://functionalflow.co.uk/blog/2013/07/21/fsharp-data-1-1-9-released"/>
    <updated>2013-07-21T22:14:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://functionalflow.co.uk/blog/2013/07/21/fsharp-data-1-1-9-released</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We've just released version <a href="http://www.nuget.org/packages/FSharp.Data/1.1.9">1.1.9</a> of <a href="http://fsharp.github.io/FSharp.Data/">FSharp.Data</a>, and I realized we've not been announcing new releases since version 1.1.1 when Tomas <a href="http://tomasp.net/blog/fsharp-data.aspx">first announced it</a>, so I though I'd rectify that. In addition to bug fixes, here what's has been added to FSharp.Data since then:</p>

<ul>
<li>The behaviour of CsvProvider can be fine tuned by using the HasHeaders, Schema, IgnoreErrors, SafeMode, and PreferOptionals parameters. See the CsvProvider documentation <a href="http://fsharp.github.io/FSharp.Data/library/CsvProvider.html">here</a>.</li>
<li>The CSV Parser and Reader can now be used standalone. See the CsvFile documentation <a href="http://fsharp.github.io/FSharp.Data/library/CsvFile.html">here</a>.</li>
<li>Guid types are now supported in CsvProvider, JsonProvider, and XmlProvider.</li>
<li>Support to disable caching for CSV files too big to fit in memory.</li>
<li>Support for cookies, binary files and client certificates in FSharp.Net.Http.</li>
<li>Save, Filter, Take, TakeWhile, Skip, SkipWhile, and Truncate operations for CsvProvider and CsvFile.</li>
<li>Support for Windows Phone 7.</li>
</ul>


<p>There's still a lot of room for improvement, and we love pull requests, so please contribute, even if it's only fixing a typo in the docs. A getting started guide is available <a href="http://fsharp.github.io/FSharp.Data/contributing.html">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Building Type Providers - Part 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://functionalflow.co.uk/blog/2013/05/13/building-type-providers-part1"/>
    <updated>2013-05-13T00:17:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://functionalflow.co.uk/blog/2013/05/13/building-type-providers-part1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Type Providers are the biggest new feature of F# 3.0. They allow us to leverage the power of the static type system in areas that have typically been the territory of dynamic languages and stringly typing. A picture is worth a thousand words, so here's 12 pictures that show type providers in action:</p>

<blockquote><p><a href="http://blogs.msdn.com/b/dsyme/archive/2013/01/30/twelve-type-providers-in-pictures.aspx">All your types are belong to us</a></p></blockquote>

<p>There are already several good samples and articles about using type providers, but there still isn't a lot about creating type providers. Having worked recently on <a href="http://fsharp.github.com/FSharp.Data/">FSharp.Data</a> I decided to share some tips about building type providers.</p>

<!-- More -->


<h2>Getting Started</h2>

<p>The basic steps to creating a type provider are:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Get the <code>ProvidedTypes.fs</code> and <code>ProvidedTypes.fsi</code> files from the <a href="http://fsharp3sample.codeplex.com/">F# 3.0 Sample Pack</a> and add it to your project.</p></li>
<li><p>Follow the instructions in <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-gb/library/hh361034.aspx">Tutorial: Creating a Type Provider</a> to create instances of <code>ProvidedTypeDefinition</code>, <code>ProvidedProperty</code>, <code>ProvidedMethod</code>, etc. in order to to define the API you want.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>After you've read that tutorial, let's carry on...</p>

<h2>Hiding the underlying representation</h2>

<p>In the simplest of cases, there's no underlying representation, so you just set the base class of your provided types to <code>obj</code>. You'll create some expressions by wrapping code in <code>&lt;@@ ... @@&gt;</code> to create quotations, and assign them to the <code>InvokeCode</code> and <code>GetterCode</code> properties of your provided methods and properties, completely ignoring the <code>this</code> argument that is passed to them. After compilation, there will be no mention whatsoever of your provided types, they will have been all erased, and the only thing left is that code you defined inside the quotations. Effectively, the type providers are only giving you syntactic sugar and IntelliSense over things you could already accomplish without using them.</p>

<p>However, in most cases, there will be some underlying data representation, and you will probably want to create some types to hold that data. A big part of the logic will be in these types, and you'll specify them as the base classes of your provided types. In this case, the F# compiler will copy and embed those base types in the assembly that is consuming the type provider. This means that in addition to the syntactic sugar, the assembly that's referencing the type providers will also have some more additional code.</p>

<p>As expected, all the members of the base types will appear on the IntelliSense of the provided types. In some situations, that's a good thing, and exactly what you wanted. On other cases (and I would guess most of the time), you intended those members to be just internal code to be used inside the implementation of the provided methods and properties, and you don't want them to show up, as after all Type Providers are mostly about providing a nice API to its users. You can see this effect on the current version of the <a href="http://www.tryfsharp.org/Learn/data-science#world-bank-type-provider">World Bank type provider on TryF#</a>. If you press the dot after <code>data</code>, you'll see that in addition to <code>Countries</code> and <code>Regions</code>, the IntelliSense pop-up will also include <code>_GetCountries</code>, <code>_GetRegions</code> and other members that aren't intended for direct use. The ideal would be for them not to show up. How can we do that?</p>

<ul>
<li>If you came from an OO background, the first thing you'd think would be to make those members protected, but there is no <code>protected</code> modifier in F#. Even if there was, you're not really creating a type and inheriting from the base type, it's all erased.</li>
<li>You can't also make those members <code>internal</code>, because your runtime representation types are always considered to belong to the type provider assembly, and not to the assembly that is using the type provider, even when the F# compiler copies those types over.</li>
<li>In C#, you can decorate methods and properties with <code>[System.ComponentModel.Browsable(false)]</code> to have them not show up on IntelliSense, but unfortunately that doesn't work in F#.</li>
<li>You can create an interface with those members, and make your runtime representation types implement that interface. That way, they won't show up on IntelliSense because F# always does explicit interface implementation. This won't work for static members though.</li>
<li>The constructors of the erased to types don't show up on the IntelliSense, so you can replace some static members like <code>Parse</code> and <code>Load</code> with constructors instead.</li>
<li>If you define a <code>ProvidedMethod</code> with the same parameter types of one of the methods of the runtime representation type, just with a different return type, that method will effectively be hidden, and you won't need to do anything to hide it.</li>
<li><code>ProvidedTypeDefinition</code> has a <code>HideObjectMethods</code> property that allows you to hide the <code>GetHashCode()</code>, <code>GetType()</code>, <code>ToString()</code> and <code>Equals</code> methods from IntelliSense, but if the base type overrides any of those methods, they will show up anyway. I still haven't found a workaround for this.</li>
</ul>


<p>The <a href="http://fsharp.github.com/FSharp.Data/">FSharp.Data</a> version of the World Bank type provider (and this also applies to the CSV, XML, JSON and Freebase type providers) uses interfaces and constructors to hide the unwanted members, so you don't see any <code>_Something</code> method.</p>

<h2>Splitting into two assemblies</h2>

<p>When the type provider starts to get bigger, you might want to separate the runtime and design-time components into two separate assemblies. You also need to do this when you want to support multiple .NET framework profiles (like Silverlight or Portable Class Libraries), where you can have a single design-time assembly, but a different runtime assembly for each profile.</p>

<p>In this scenario, the design-time assembly can't just reference the runtime assembly, because there are multiple versions of them. And even if you're not supporting multiple profiles, the design-time assemblies of type providers are loaded inside the F# compiler process, which makes any assembly dependency for the design-time component to not work correctly. To work around this, usually there's no dependency between the design-time assembly and the runtime assembly, and instead we include all the files of the runtime assembly directly in the design-time assembly. This may increase the size of the design-time component, but it's not a big deal because that dll doesn't need to be included in the final application.</p>

<p>But with this solution, comes a big problem: your quotations will stop working. Why? Because you're referencing the types of the wrong assembly. To overcome this, the <code>TypeProviderConfig</code> that is passed to your type provider has a <code>RuntimeAssembly</code> property which allows you to load the runtime component using <code>Assembly.LoadFrom</code>, get the types you need using <code>Assembly.GetType</code>, and construct your expressions manually from that. Most of the samples in the <a href="http://fsharp3sample.codeplex.com/">F# 3.0 Sample Pack</a> use this. Great, problem solved, right?</p>

<p>Back in January, I started adding support for portable class libraries in <a href="http://fsharp.github.com/FSharp.Data/">FSharp.Data</a> because I wanted to use it on some Windows Phone and Windows 8 apps. After changing a couple of places from quotations to manually creating expression and using the reflection API, I though to myself:</p>

<blockquote><p>"No! The code was nice and clean with type safe quotations, and now I'm turning it to this mess with error prone reflection calls using a stringly typed api. It's a huge step back. There has to be a better way."</p></blockquote>

<p>And eventually after a couple of failed attempts and a lot of discussion on the github issue, I finally arrived at a solution: process the quotations to fix the type references to the right assembly. This is done by <code>AssemblyReplacer</code>, which you can find <a href="https://github.com/fsharp/FSharp.Data/blob/master/src/Providers/AssemblyReplacer.fs">here</a>. It's pretty much independent of the rest of <a href="http://fsharp.github.com/FSharp.Data/">FSharp.Data</a>, so you can just copy it over to your type provider project if you need it.</p>

<p>There are places where even without splitting the type provider into a design-time and runtime assembly, it isn't possible to use quotations, and you still need to keep creating expressions manually. That only happens when you use generics parameterized by a type generated by the type provider. For those, cases <a href="http://tomasp.net/">Tomas</a> has created a nice dynamic operator (?) implementation in <code>QuotationBuilder</code> which is available <a href="https://github.com/fsharp/FSharp.Data/blob/master/src/Providers/QuotationBuilder.fs">here</a>.</p>

<h2>Coming Next</h2>

<ul>
<li>Debugging type providers</li>
<li>Supporting multiple .NET framework profiles</li>
<li>Common errors found during type provider development</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
